There is only one thing which I want to mention
more in every, you know very, very high level
I do not want to get into the proofs and other
things the guys who did the course last year
actually had a guest lecture from somebody
who works in this field and who was able to
talk about another technique which is gaining
a lot of popularity recently, so he talked
about that in a gory detail in fact it did
some proofs from one of the papers that they
wrote and so on so forth but unfortunately
I do not have the guest lecturer here this
time and was also I mean just I introduce
you that ideas to you and then if you want
you can read up on those later right but in
some sense.
Whatever we have done so far gives you all
the tools that you need you know it gives
you the basic tools for it understand more
complex algorithms and so on so forth so that
is the whole idea for me to do this and if
you actually look at the book right the textbook.
They almost in passing mention all of these
algorithms mean they'll have like one paragraph
saying oh this is how you do you see be and
this is how you do they don't talk about meeting
limitation at all this is how you do something
else which i will talk about in the next class
called reinforce and they mention these things
in passing and then they say we will build
on some of these ideas as and when required
for the full reinforcement learning problem
right.
So in some sense the book treats bandits as
something that you is a necessary evil that
you need to know about on your way to learning
about the full RL problem right.
Given the focus of the book that's a valid
way of treating bandit problems but in fact
it bandits itself is a very, very rich large
literature and it is very active area of research
for a lot of rain for running people.
And this one of the reasons I actually covered
bandits in a little more depth.
Then I used to do maybe a couple of years
ago, right.
So couple of years ago.
I did bandits in like one class, right all
of bandits.
Anyway so we one thing which I want to talk
about was,
.
Thompson sampling which is gaining a lot of
attraction now okay, so it is more descriptively
you could call it posterior sampling depending
on which literature reading some people call
it posterior sampling some people call It
Thompson sampling so the basic idea is the
following right, So I am trying to solve the
Bandit problem right and we know that if you
know that the parameters of the Bandit if
I knew all the Q stars right I can solve it
very easily right so how what do i do, take
the highest right so what I am going to do
when I do this kind of Thomson sampling approach
is to, take a somewhat Belgian way of looking
at these things.
That I am going to say that ok I am solving
this unknown problem, I am solving this unknown
problem.
But I am going to make some assumption about
the parameters of this unknown problem.
Right so essentially and the assumption I'm
making here is about the, Q stars I am going
to make an assumption that the true Q stars
come from some distribution right.
I will start with some guess for this the
2Q stars come from some distribution ,right
so if my if my if I know that my rewards are
limited between0 and 1 like for like many
of the cases we have been assuming the rewards
are limited between 0 and 1 so what would
be an appropriate assumption for this Q star
distribution .Beta distribution so people
remember beta distribution, the guys who are
in ml, the guys who are in ml at least should
remember the beta distribution so the beta
distribution is is a distribution that is
limited to zero one right and take all kinds
of weird Falls right and ,so this is typically
a prior that prior distribution that use you
whenever you have.
We are trying to find parameters of a, distribution
where the parameter is limited between zero
and one ok so the beta distribution is a very
popular prior that is used as like that I
make some kind of an assumption let us say
that i do not know anything about the underlying
problem right.
Then what will I assume, uniform right you
can assume a uniform distribution saying that
I don't know anything so my Q starts can come
from anywhere so now what do I do and one
way of solving this problem is to say that
given my current knowledge about the parameters
It given my current knowledge about the parameters
which arm should I play okay.
So that I may reward is optimized that is
one way of thinking about it so what should
i do then i should take each bandit combination
right I should I should say that ok, ok the
probability of it so Q star 1 is some value
say 0.3 Q star 2 is 0.5 Q star3 is something
else 1.2 like that so I have to make one bandit
problem and then figure out okay what is your
best term to play here and then take another
bandage problem figure out what is the best
term to play if you take another banded problem
figure out what is the best term to play and
for each of these Bandit problems.
I should look at what is the probability that
this is the true Q stars according to my current
knowledge about the problem so if I start
off with a uniform distributions and everything
is equally likely right so all arms I mean
can be optimal all arms can be non optimal
and so on so forth so I basically have to
play at random right but it turns out that
doing this computation can be very, very cumbersome
you can just think about it right I am asking
you to figure out for each arm combination
with what is the probability that the arm
combination can occur right and depending
on the nature of the probability distributions
you are assuming this computation can become
very, very complex right.
So the posterior sampling idea is a way of
approximating this computation so what I do
is the following is very, very simple okay.
I have some distribution over what my Q star
values will be have some distribution over
by Q star values so what I do is I draw a
sample from the distribution.
Right so let us say something like this so
my.
(Refer Slide Time: 7: 06)
So Q star1 I am saying is something like this
right and then, that Q star2.
Tats Q star 3 .You have another color okay
oh you're good four arms because running out
of colors.
Right so Q star 1 2 3 4 right this is the
current distribution i have so i am assuming
that the true value of Q star lies somewhere
in this range, right and it is most probably
this value but I do not know yet right there
is some uncertainty about what the values
are now what I do is, I draw samples you remembered
we talked about drawing samples from Gaussians
and other distributions I draw samples so
I draw a so basically right so, this is basically
my reward.
.
This my reward axis and these are the probability
axis I draw a sample for that is one this
is another that Is another Right.
So now I have a specific bandit problem where
my Q star 1 is this Q star 2 is this Q star
3 is this and Q star 4 is this so I have taken
this distribution right and I have drawn one
bandit problem from this distribution okay
now I solve this problem the very basically
pull on three because one thing gives me gave
me the best value here so I pull on three
now I look at the actual reward I get four
on three.
.
Let's I pull on three and let us say that
my on three reward is that this is the actual
reward that I get four on three and now I
go back and update this fellow based on this
reward right so what ,what do you think it
should be.
.
Look um narrower because this is I kind of
reinforcing my original belief that this is
the most probable outcome.
.
So
this will become my belief now this is my
new distribution now again I try to sample
so the probability that I will sample a high
value for the green arm goes down now because
I when I played the green arm I got a smaller
vent so I keep doing this until my probability
is kind of converged to the 2Q stars at the
time in a sample a problem from there I will
most probably be sampling that true problem
right the actual problem underlying that which
I am trying to solve this .This is called
Thompson sampling or posterior sampling.
So this is getting a lot of attention recently
mainly because people have been able to show
that this can give you better regret bounce
than you see be right so this can give you
better regret bones than you see be and therefore
there is a lot of attention that's being paid
to Thompson sampling approaches.
The analysis gets really hairy and in fact
until recently there was no analysis of the
Thompson sampling approach but more recently
there have been several three four years there
have been several papers that they have come
up with new techniques for analyzing these
kinds of algorithms different from what we
have been talking about so far.
Kind around based right yeah.
We are not eliminating any arms this what
you are saying right well it turns out that
you don't have to even without eliminating
arms you are getting very good complexity
and typically what happens is after some time
the posteriors become so focused right so
the probability of you actually selecting
the bad arm is gone I mean if you do not really
need to do a round based computation there
but yeah there might be a room for sorry after
a few steps yeah I mean yeah this is possibility
so the only thing is the only tricky part
is once you do this kind of elimination glad
to come back and analyze it.
So you saw how to keep this we came right
I mean I gave you the right events to consider
here right but to come up with these events
is a tricky part right so once you come up
with these events is easy to bound the probabilities
and how do you know that this is the actual
set of conditions that you should consider
right for you to prove the whistle so that
is the tricky part now once I say that okay
here is a round based Thompson sampling approach
then going and showing that it actually gives
you the guarantees that you want becomes tricky
I mean people just the plain Thompson sampling
without any round basing itself resisted analysis
for what a decade right and so, so it's not,
not immediately clear.
Whether there is more interesting result that
have come in yeah so people there is a very
old style algorithm very world class of algorithms
for solving bandit problems called learning
automate and algorithm these are the people
know about finite state machines right all
of you know about finite state machines and
have bunch of states and have some input signals
symbols coming and then you jump around the
states and so on so forthright.
So there is a class of finite state machines
called variable structured finite state machines
variable structure automata right and people
have used variable structure automator to
solve banded problems I am going to get into
the details of it right so it's and it turns
out that some of what the variable structure
automate algorithms are doing is posterior
sampling it turns out to be very similar to
posterior sampling and very recently and earlier
we knew results only for asymptotic convergence
of this learning automaton algorithms.
So very recently like late last year October
or November of last year people have shown
that they also satisfy regret bonds they satisfy
the block t regret bonds so that means a lot
of interesting work that's happening in this
phase and I mean of course If you're welcome
to try a round based a thousand sampling algorithm
I don't know or we just check on arcade right
the rate at which work comes out in this space
and make me something already out there okay.
So stop here in the next class we will look
at ways of solving the Bandit problem which
do not depend on the do not depend on estimating
the value function so everything you have
looked on so far look finds the function Q
right capital key so next class we look at
one class of algorithms which do not look
at maintaining the value function and directly
try to learn the probabilities which you share
to select the arms.